Markham Starr collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Markham Starr collection 2005-2019
AFC 2013/031
Starr, Markham
1751 items
18 documents: digital, pdf, doc, xls, and txt
1665 photographs: digital, tif, jpg, black-and-white
8 audio files: digital, wav
56 video files: digital, mov, mp4, m2t, m2ts, avi
4 volumes (.3 linear feet)
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of 1747 digital files of graphic, moving image, sound recording, and manuscript format documentary works created by Markham Starr and four of his published monographs. The collection primarily documents northeastern fishermen and the fishing industry. Some records also document farming and dairy production. A majority of the works are part of larger themed documentary projects, and others are independent works.
Provenance
Markham Starr; Donation; 2013, 2015, 2018, 2019, 2020.
The collection was acquired from Starr in five separate accruals, 2013-2020. The film in Series 2 ('Scalloping on the Mister G') was originally received as a DVD and Starr delivered a replacement digital file to the archive in February 2021.
Accruals
Further accruals expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Markham Starr collection is open to research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Markham Starr is a documentary photographer, writer, and filmmaker from Connecticut. He is active in the northeastern United States. His primary interests are fisherman and the fishing industry, and has also documented farming and dairy production, among other arts and trades. His particular focus is documenting industries and individuals experiencing change due to industrialization, technological advancements, globalization, or government regulation.
Scope and Content
Collection of 1747 digital files of graphic, moving image, sound recording, and manuscript format documentary works created by Markham Starr, and 4 of Starr's published monographs. The collection primarily documents northeastern United States fisherman and the fishing industry. Some records also document farming and dairy production. Starr created the records in the collection between 2005 and 2019. The works often focus on individuals and businesses experiencing change due to industrialization, technological advancements, globalization, or government regulation. Many of the moving image, sound recording, and manuscript works feature first-person narratives from interview subjects. The discussions concern their experience as workers and the ways their work has changed during their careers. Some of the records feature detailed discussions and demonstrations of technical processes and skilled techniques. The graphic materials depict individuals at work or in portrait,worksites, and trade tools, machinery, and implements. A majority of the works are associated with one of Starr's larger themed documentary projects, but the sound recordings and some of the moving images are independent works.
Starr selected works from his projects to donate to the American Folklife Center. Besides those that stand alone, the records are drawn from six themed documentary projects. The names of the projects and the years they were conducted are:
End of the Line: Closing the Last Sardine Cannery in America, March 2010.
Finest Kind: The Lobstermen of Corea Maine, June and July 2010.
Against the Tide: The Commercial Fishermen of Point Judith RI, 2005-2013.
Down On The Farm: The Last Dairy Farms of North Stonington, 2007-2010.
In History's Wake: The Last Trap Fishermen of RI, 2008-2018.
Voices From The Waterfront: Portrait of the New Bedford Fishing Industry, 2009.
These projects resulted in published books, which are titled with the same names. Digital drafts or final publications of the books are included in this collection's manuscript materials. Additionally, some of the titles have physical printed copies also included in the collection (series 6). Starr's descriptions of these projects can be found in the manuscripts, especially the books.
The bulk of the collection is graphic materials and moving images. The graphic materials are all associated with one of the six documentary projects and are grouped by project. The moving images are roughly divided into two equal groupings: those that are part of In History's Wake: The Last Trap Fishermen of RI, and those that are independent works. All but one of the moving images concerns fishing and fishermen - the outlier is about a Preston, Connecticut farmer and his family dairy farm. Most of the fishing films, including the independent works, are shot in Rhode Island and concern the region's fish industry. The films vary in length from short to feature length. The sound recordings are interviews with Rhode Island trap fishermen; however Starr indicates that these recordings were conducted separately from his In History's Wake: The Last Trap Fishermen of RI project.
Starr's manuscripts are either associated with a documentary project or are descriptive aids for the collection. The descriptive aids are spreadsheets and text documents and contain item level information for each file. Archivists repurposed, with very minimal edits, much of Starr's guides into the titles and item-level Scope and Content notes in this finding aid. The guides contain some additional information such as locations and camera equipment used. The descriptive documents in each series are:
Series 1. 2013 accrual (afc2013031_dc001): "manifest_ph0001-ph0336_inventory.xls" and "manifest_ph0337-ph0824_inventory.xls"
Series 2. 2015 accrual (afc2013031_dc002): "Against the Tide The Commercial Fishermen of Point Judith RI.xls," "Down on the Farm The Last Dairy Farms of North Stonington.xls," "In Historys Wake The Last Trap Fishermen of RI.xls," and "Voices From the Waterfront Portraits From the New Bedford Fishing Industry.xls"
Series 3. 2018 accrual (afc2013031_dc003): "FILES.docx"
Series 4. 2019 accrual (afc2013031_dc004): "afc2013031_Interview_Descriptions.doc"
Series 5. 2020 accrual (afc2013031_dc005): "Descriptions of the films on this hard drive.txt"
Arrangement
The Markham Starr collection is arranged in 6 series. Series 1 through Series 5 each correspond to one accrual from the donor. Series 6 is a small grouping of four of Starr's printed books. The series are:
Series 1. 2013 accrual: End of the Line: Closing the Last Sardine Cannery in America and Finest Kind: The Lobstermen of Corea Maine files, March 1, 2010 through March 30, 2010, June 28 2010 through July 30 2010.
Subseries 1. End of the Line: Closing the Last Sardine Cannery in America files, March 1, 2010 through March 30, 2010
Subseries 2. Finest Kind: The Lobstermen of Corea Maine files, June 28 2010 through July 30 2010
Series 2. 2015 accrual: Against the Tide: The Commercial Fishermen of Point Judith RI, Down On The Farm: The Last Dairy Farms of North Stonington, In History's Wake: The Last Trap Fishermen of RI, and Voices From The Waterfront: Portrait of the New Bedford Fishing Industry photographs, March 26, 2005 through December 4, 2013.
Subseries 1. Against the Tide: The Commercial Fishermen of Point Judith RI files, March 26, 2005 through December 2, 2013
Subseries 2. Down On The Farm: The Last Dairy Farms of North Stonington files, October 2, 2007 through November 2010
Subseries 3. In History's Wake: The Last Trap Fishermen of RI files, April 8, 2008 through 2010
Subseries 4. Voices From The Waterfront: Portrait of the New Bedford Fishing Industry files, April 8, 2008 through 2010
Series 3. 2018 accrual: In History's Wake: The Last Trap Fishermen of RI moving images, circa 2010-2018.
Subseries 1. General audience films
Subseries 2. Technical films
Series 4. 2019 accrual: Interview transcripts and sound recordings, circa 2005-2019.
Series 5. 2020 accrual: Independent films, circa 2010-2019.
Series 6. Published materials 2010-2015.
The contents and arrangements of each series are described in the series-level Scope and Content and Arrangement notes.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Starr, Markham; Starr, Markham. Against the tide: the commercial fishermen of Point Judith. 2009.; Starr, Markham. Down on the farm: the last dairy farms of North Stonington. 2010.; Starr, Markham. Finest kind: the lobstermen of Corea, portrait of a down east fishing village. 2011.; Starr, Markham. In history's wake: the last trap fishermen of Rhode Island. 2010.; Starr, Markham. Swab summer: transformation at the United States Coast Guard Academy. 2013.
Organizations
Stinson Seafood--Photographs.; United States Coast Guard Academy--Pictorial works.
Subjects
Canned fish industry--Maine--Photographs.; Canned sardines--Maine--Photographs.; Cannery workers--Maine--Photographs.; Dairy farms--Connecticut--North Stonington--Pictorial works.; Dairy farms--Connecticut--Video recordings.; Documentary films.; Documentary photography.; Fish canneries--Maine--Photographs.; Fish trapping--Rhode Island--Pictorial works.; Fish trapping--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Fisheries--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Fishers--Rhode Island--Pictorial works.; Fishing baits--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Fishing boats--Maine--Photographs.; Fishing boats--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Fishing ports--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Fishing--Rhode Island--Pictorial works.; Fishmongers--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Gillnetting--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Lobster fishers--Maine--Photographs.; Lobster fishers--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Lobster industry--Maine--Photographs.; Machinists--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Occupational folklore--New England.; Oystering--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Scallop industry--Rhode Island--Video recordings.; Scallop industry--Rhode Island--Video recordings.
Places
Block Island (R.I.: Island); Corea (Me.); Hancock County (Me.); North Stonington (Conn.); Point Judith (R.I.); Preston (Conn.); Rhode Island.
Titles
Scallop Fishing on the MISTER G.; Voices From The Waterfront: Portrait of the New Bedford Fishing Industry.
Form/Genre
Digital photographs--2000-2010.; Interviews.; Portrait photographs--2000-2010.; Video recordings.
Container List
- Series 1. 2013 accrual: End of the Line and Finest Kind files, March 1, 2010 through March 30, 2010, June 28 2010 through July 30 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 822 TIFF, 2 jpg, 2 pdf, 2 xls, and 1 docx
  Accrual is 824 images, 2 corresponding spreadsheets, 2 book pdfs, and 1 manuscript. The files concern two of Starr's documentary projects: End of the Line: Closing the Last Sardine Cannery in America and Finest Kind: The Lobstermen of Corea Maine. The photos are from two documentary trips; the Lobstermen photos are from June and July 2010 and the Cannery photos are from March 2010, primarily the 29th and 30th. See the Biographical Note for further descriptions of the projects. The photos generally depict subjects at work, tools and implements, and worksites. Every photo has an item level description, which are saved with the photos in two spreadsheets - see this series' Arrangement Note for more information. The PDF 'Finest Kind The Lobstermen of Corea Maine.pdf' is a copy of Starr's book by the same name. In addition to copies of the photographs, it contains transcribed interviews with a dozen fisherman and their families, extensive information about the lobster fishing trade and industry, and descriptions of Starr's project. The PDF 'The Last Sardine The Closing of the Stinson Cannery.pdf' only contains copies of Starr's photographs. The word document 'afc2013031_ms01.docx' is Starr's description of the Cannery documentary project.
  Starr assigned unique IDs to the images in this accrual. The unique ids are a sequential number starting from zero. The file 'manifest_ph0001-ph0336_inventory.xls' contains the Starr's descriptions for the Cannery project photos, and 'manifest_ph0337-ph0824_inventory.xls' contains his descriptions for the Lobsterman photos. The unique IDs match the descriptions to filenames. Dates, when provided in the spreadsheets, appear to be inaccurate. The images' Exif metadata appears to have more reliable date information. The files are all in one folder.
  - Subseries 1. End of the Line: Closing the Last Sardine Cannery in America files, March 1, 2010 through March 30, 2010, 334 TIFF, 2 jpg, 1 docx, 1 pdf, 1 xls
    Photographs created during Starr's visit to the Stinson Cannery in 2010. Also included is one manuscript document containing Starr's description of the photography project, a PDF containing copies of the photographs, and one inventory spreadsheet containing descriptive data for every photo.
    The digital files on disk have not been rearranged from their original order. The manuscript files have been described in alphabetical order in the finding aid and the photographs are listed in numerical order by ID number. The photographs' titles and ID numbers are copied from Starr's item level metadata in the photo inventory "manifest_ph0001-ph0336_inventory.xls". The descriptions are used as titles. If a description was too long to be an effective title archivists shortened it and recorded the original description in the item's Scope and Content note. The dates come from the photographs' EXIF metadata, except where that data is clearly inaccurate. In those cases archivists estimated an accurate date. See the inventory and files' metadata for more context.
    - A Description of the Stinson Cannery Photo Project, March 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 docx
    - The Last Sardine: The Closing of the Stinson Cannery, March 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 pdf
    - Photo inventory, March 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 xls
    - View of the Stinson factory from the other side of Prospect Harbor with a lobster boat in foreground, March 28, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Part of the village of Prospect Harbor, Maine as seen from across the harbor, March 28, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Architectural detail on a home in Prospect Harbor, ME, March 16, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Front view of the Down East Deli, March 16, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Front view of the Down East Deli. One of the few stores on the main street through the village, even this store was up for sale.
    - View of the Stinson factory from the other side of Prospect Harbor with fishing boats in the harbor, March 16, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      View of the Stinson factory from the other side of Prospect Harbor with fishing boats in the harbor. While there is still some dragging, scalloping, and sea-urchin fishing still going on in the area, it is very minor. Almost all fishing effort involves lobstering this far down east.
    - Beach Cliff Sardine sign at entrance to Stinson's, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Beach Cliff Sardine sign at entrance to Stinson's. Known as Big Jim, this sign was once used to welcome people to Maine on the highway. Originally made in wood, it was being taken down and Stinson brought it to Prospect Harbor and it became the symbol on the Beech Cliff brand of sardines. The sign was rebuilt in metal. His boots are over five feet tall.
    - Big Jim from the front, March 1, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Big Jim from the back, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - View of the facility looking from the wharf towards the mouth of the harbor, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      View of the facility looking from the wharf towards the mouth of the harbor. The wharf is where fresh sardines were landed by boat. Sardine carriers would tie up here and the fish was pumped from their holds. Stinson's eventually took in frozen fish as well by truck to extend their processing schedule. On the left is where overboard discharged was screened out through roto-strainers. The bait area is just a little bit to the right - cuttings and whole bait for lobstermen.
    - View further down on back side of plant - used to be can manufacturing section - turned into the casing operation, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      View further down on back side of plant - used to be can manufacturing section - turned into the casing operation. Cans made in 1960 until around 2003 or '04. The can making machinery was then sent to Blacks Harbor when Connors Brothers took over in 2000 until 2005 - then BumbleBee purchased the factory.
    - Outside of plant - air-handling equipment, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - One section of a warehouse used to store products and supplies, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Back of boiler room. Dumpsters and behind them a 10,000 gallon bunker-C oil tank, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Back of boiler room. Dumpsters and behind them a 10,000 gallon bunker-C oil tank. Storage buildings to the left. There were two, 200 hp boilers - Superior Boilers for steam. Steam used for processing, heated water for the can washer, the retorts, and to heat the building. Burned 1100 gallons a day in winter. Summer, 400-700 gallons, depending on the production of the day. All steam to the steam boxes was in and out - not recovered. Heaters were recovered and condensate brought back into boiler room. All equipment and chimney removed after plant closed.
    - Three - ten thousand gallon water tanks, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Three - ten thousand gallon water tanks. Water comes from two artesian wells about a mile away and is stored in those tanks - reserve for production. Fresh water. In 2009 line was run underground and across the harbor to supply factory - very good water.
    - De-watering tower, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      De-watering tower - screen the water out as fish were pumped from carry boats before it went into tank trucks or totes.
    - Crane used to lower suction-hose into fish carrier, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Crane used to lower suction-hose into fish carrier. Army surplus crane from Massachusetts. Found in junk-yard. Alexander welding made new OSHA approved framework.
    - Side entryway and signs, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Floorplan of factory, March 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 jpg
      Floorplan of factory - taken from emergency exit plan for building.
    - Early morning view of de-watering tower, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Early morning view of de-watering tower and lobster traps on dock next door, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - First workers coming in for the day - around 5:30 AM, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Coats hanging in one of the staff locker rooms, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Frozen blocks of herring - 40 or 50 lb. blocks when fresh fish couldn't be had, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Frozen blocks of herring - 40 or 50 lb. blocks when fresh fish couldn't be had. Last 3 months of production were frozen. Frozen fish made scheduling easier -they knew how long the day would be. The problem was the amount of fish they could thaw and produce each day was less than they could do with fresh fish. Early years they processed fish from the spring to late fall as fish were caught along coast. In 1960's they went into purse-seining, in deeper waters, and that allowed them to get more fish for the winter time, so they started producing in the winter as well. 1980's-90's pair-trawling allowed them to fish in even deeper water and rougher weather. Purse-seining you had a small boat that had to encircle the fish which couldn't be done in rough weather. When the quotas began in the 2000 era, reductions occurred in the amount of fish that could be caught, so they got frozen fish to supplement their catch. Fish were then caught in November and December when the fish were clean and in good shape, and they would freeze the amount they needed for April, May and even into June. That allowed Stinson's to produce year-round. The fish were brought in and frozen on shore. The bulk of the frozen fish came from New Jersey, and some from New Bedford. Stinson's didn't have their own freezers.
    - Frozen blocks of herring, March 30, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Frozen blocks of herring, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Frozen blocks of herring, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Frozen blocks of herring, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Cardboard boxes from which frozen herring had been removed, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Cardboard boxes from which frozen herring had been removed. Cardboard was recycled.
    - Pallets of frozen herring moved down to the tank room, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Pallets of frozen herring moved down to the tank room. Fish would thaw in this area throughout the day until loaded into tanks for thawing over night. This fish would be the next day's production.
    - Tank room, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      Tank room. They would offload anywhere from 40,000-50,000 pounds from a truck or as much as 120,000 -140,000 pounds of fish from a boat. They could hold those fish overnight in refrigerated brine. It was an ammonia system used to cool the brine tank - temperatures maintained below 40 degrees - this would preserve them overnight so the enzymes wouldn't ruin the fish. Each tank on the left side of the photo would hold about 10,000 pounds of fish and there were 11 of those tanks. On the right side they were smaller tanks and would hold about 8000 pounds of fish, and there were eight tanks there.
    - Man flumed the fish out of the tanks and into separators, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      This man flumed the fish out of the tanks and into separators. All the fish had to be separated by size prior to cutting so there was a uniform size going to the cutting machines. The thickness of the fish would determine the length of the fish as well. The fish were sent down a series of parallel rollers spaced at various distances apart from one another. The smallest fish would fall through the rollers first and onto a conveyor belt that would take them away. As the distance between rollers increased, larger fish would fall through to their own conveyor by size. Water sprayed on the fish in these images keeps the fish lubricated and separated from each other to aid the sorting process.
    - PVC piping that brought fresh fish from trucks or boats into the tanks along with water to help fill them, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
      PVC piping that brought fresh fish from trucks or boats into the tanks along with water to help fill them. Fish, offloaded from either boats or trucks, would be flumed down to these tanks via these pipes. Trucks would offload onto a conveyor, boats directly into pipework. The "Ts" in the photo could be raised or lowered to fill any particular tank. When the tank was full, the T was raised and the fish went to the next tank. These pipes also added water to fill the tanks more quickly.
    - Three workers unload frozen fish into tanks for thawing. Renaldo Perez on right, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Fish thawing in tanks - agitated with air and circulation but kept below 50 degrees, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF
    - Man on left Humberto Garcia, man on right is probably Jose Rodriguez. They would offload the fish out of the tanks and fill the tank back up with water, March 29, 2010, afc2013031_dc001; 1 TIFF